A month ago today
من شهر واحد بالضبط
I stood there:
لقد وقفت هناك
90 degrees south, the top of
90 درجة جنوبا في قمة
the bottom of the world, the Geographic South Pole.
اسفل العالم . القطب الجنوبي الجغرافي
And I stood there beside two very good friends of mine,
و لقد وقفت هناك مع اثنين من اعز اصقائي
Richard Weber and Kevin Vallely.
ريتشارد ويبر و كيفن فالي
Together we had just broken the world speed record
معا كنا قد حطمنا الرقم القياسي العالمي للسرعة
for a trek to the South Pole.
في السير على الاقدام للقطب الحنوبي
It took us 33 days,
و لقد استغرقنا ذلك 33 يوما
23 hours and 55 minutes to get there.
و 23 ساعة و 55 دقيقة للوصول هناك
We shaved five days off the previous best time.
لقد كسرنا الرقم العالمي السابق بخمسة ايام
And in the process, I became the first person in history
و من ضمن هذه التجربة اصبحت اول شخص في التاريخ
to make the entire 650-mile journey,
يقطع الرحلة كاملة و البالغة 1050 كم
from Hercules Inlet to South Pole,
من منطقة هيركيوليس الى القطب الجنوبي
solely on feet, without skis.
على لاقدام فقط و من غير زلاجات
Now, many of you are probably saying, "Wait a sec,
قد يتسائل العديد منكم الان "انتظر قليلا
is this tough to do?"
هل هذا الانجاز صعب التحقيق؟"
(Laughter)
- ضحك من الجمهور -
Imagine, if you will,
تخيل ان اردت ذلك
dragging a sled, as you just saw in that video clip,
جارا خلفك - كما هو موضح في الفيديو كليب-
with 170 pounds of gear,
80 كغ من المعدات
in it everything you need to survive on your Antarctic trek.
و فيها كل ما تحتاجه للبقاء على الحياة في رحلتك لقارة انتاركتيكا
It's going to be 40 below, every single day.
و الحرارة 40 تحت الصفر كل يوم
You'll be in a massive headwind.
مع رياح معاكسة قوية جدا
And at some point you're going to have to cross these cracks in the ice,
و في بعض المراحل يجب عليك اجتياز الاخاديد في الجليد
these crevasses.
بعض هذه الاخاديد
Some of them have a very precarious thin footbridge underneath them
لها ممرات هشة جدا فوقها
that could give way at a moment's notice,
ممكن ان تنهار بسرعة جدا
taking your sled, you, into the abyss, never to be seen again.
و تأخذك انت و زلاجتك الى الهاوية حيث لا يمكن ان ترى بعدها ابدا
The punchline to your journey? Look at the horizon.
لترى خط النهاية لرحلتك انظر الى الافق
Yes, it's uphill the entire way,
نعم , ان الطريق كله صعود
because the South Pole is at 10,000 feet,
لان القطب الجنوبي يرتفع 3000 متر
and you're starting at sea level.
و الرحلة تبدا من سطح البحر
Our journey did not, in fact, begin at Hercules Inlet,
ان رحلتنا في الواقع لم تبدأ من خليج هيركيوليس
where frozen ocean meets the land of Antarctica.
حيث تلتقي مياه المحيط المتجمد مع ارض قارة انتاركتيكا
It began a little less than two years ago.
لقد بدأت قبل ذلك بعامين
A couple of buddies of mine and I
انا و صديقين لي
had finished a 111-day run across the entire Sahara desert.
كنا قد انهينا جولة من الركض لمدة 111 يوم عبر صحراء "سهارا" في افريقيا
And while we were there we learned
و خلال ذلك علمنا
the seriousness of the water crisis in Northern Africa.
عن خطورة كارثة المياه في شمال افريقيا
We also learned that many of the issues facing the people of Northern Africa
و علمنا ايضا الكثير عن عن المشاكل التي تواجه سكان شمال افريقيا
affected young people the most.
اكثر ما تؤثر على الشباب
I came home to my wife after 111 days of running in the sand,
بعد 111 يوم من الركض في الرمال , اتيت لزوجتي و قلت
and I said, "You know, there's no doubt if this bozo can get across the desert,
تعلمين انه لا شك بانني اقدر على عبور الصحراء
we are capable of doing anything we set our minds to."
اننا قادرون على فعل اي شيئ نصمم عليه
But if I'm going to continue doing these adventures, there has to be
و لكن لا بد من وجود سبب لي
a reason for me to do them
للقيام بهذه المغامرات
beyond just getting there.
اكثر من مجرد الصول الى نقطة معينة
Around that time I met an extraordinary human being,
و خلال ذلك الوقت التقيت بانسان استثنائي يدعى بيتر ثام
Peter Thum, who inspired me with his actions.
الهمني بافعاله
He's trying to find and solve water issues, the crisis around the world.
بيتر يحاول ايجاد و حل مشاكل المياه و هي المشكلة العالمية
His dedication inspired me to come up with this expedition:
و الهمني تفانيه بالقيام بهذه الرحلة
a run to the South Pole
و هي العدو الى القطب الجنوبي
where, with an interactive website,
و بحيث استطيع من خلال موقع تفاعلي على الانترنت
I will be able to bring young people, students and teachers from around the world
ان اصطحب معي الشباب و الطلاب و المدرسين من انحاء العالم
on board the expedition with me,
في هذه الرحلة
as active members.
كأعضاء فاعلين
So we would have a live website, that every single day of the 33 days,
و هكذا كان لدينا موقع تفاعلي على الانترنت, و كل يوم من ال 33 يوم
we would be blogging, telling stories of,
كنا نكتب عن كل شيئ و نقص قصصا عن
you know, depleted ozone forcing us to cover our faces,
اضمحلال طبقة الاوزون مما يجبرنا على تغطية وجوهنا
or we will burn.
و الا سوف نصاب بالحروق
Crossing miles and miles of sastrugi --
او الكتاية عن التلال الثلجية الحادة الاطراف
frozen ice snowdrifts that could be hip-deep.
و التي يصل ارتفاعها الى متر كامل
I'm telling you, crossing these things with 170-pound sled,
تخيل عبور هذه الاشياء مع زلاجة يصل وزنها الى 80 كغ
that sled may as well have weighed 1,700 pounds,
و لكني كنت احس بالوزن و كأنه
because that's what it felt like.
800 كغ
We were blogging to this live website daily
كنا نكتب يوميا على الموقع
to these students that were tracking us as well,
للطلاب الذين كانوا يتابعوننا
about 10-hour trekking days,
بعض الايام كنا نمشي لمدة 10 ساعات
15-hour trekking days,
بعض الايام كنا نمشي لمدة 15ساعة
sometimes 20 hours of trekking daily to meet our goal.
و احيانا كنا نمشي لمدة 20 ساعة حتى نحقق اهداف الخطة
We'd catch cat-naps at 40 below on our sled, incidentally.
و احيانا كنا ننام لفترات قصيرة في حرارة 40 تحت الصفر على الزلاجات
In turn, students,
و في المقابل , كان الطلاب
people from around the world, would ask us questions.
و الاشخاص من حول العالم يسألوننا الاسئلة
Young people would ask the most amazing questions.
و كان الشباب و الاطفال يسألون اسئلة مدهشة
One of my favorite: It's 40 below, you've got to go to the bathroom,
احد الاسئلة المفضلة كان : كيف تذهبون الى دورة المياه في درجة حرارة 40 تحت الصفر؟
where are you going to go and how are you going to do it?
اين ستذهبون و كيف ستقومون بذلك؟
I'm not going to answer that. But I will answer some of the more popular questions.
لن اجاوب الان عن هذا السؤال و لكن سأجيب عن اسئلة مفضلة اخرى
Where do you sleep? We slept in a tent that was very low to the ground,
اين تنامون؟ كنا ننام في خيام قليلة الارتفاع و قريبة من الارض
because the winds on Antarctica were so extreme, it would blow anything else away.
لان الرياح قوية جدا بحيث تزيل كل شيئ في طريقها
What do you eat? One of my favorite dishes on expedition:
ماذا تأكلون ؟ ان احد اطباق المفضلة هو الزبدة و اللحم
butter and bacon. It's about a million calories.
لاحتوائه على مليون حريرة (كالوري).....
We were burning about 8,500 a day,
كنا نستهلك يوميا حوالي 8500 سعرة حرارية
so we needed it.
لذلك كنا نحتاج طعام عالي القيمة الغذائية
How many batteries do you carry for all the equipment that you have?
كم بطارية كان معكم لتشغيل الاجهزة التي تحملونها؟
Virtually none. All of our equipment, including film equipment,
لم يكن معنا اية بطاريات, لان جميع الاجهزة التي كانت معنا و اجهزة التصوير
was charged by the sun.
كانت تعمل بالطاقة الشمسية
And do you get along? I certainly hope so,
و هل كنتم متفاهمين مع بعض؟ بالتأكيد اتمنى ذلك
because at some point or another on this expedition,
لانه خلال الرحلة و في نقطة ما
one of your teammates is going to have to take a very big needle,
سيقوم احد اعضار الفريق بأخذ ابرة كبيرة جدا
and put it in an infected blister, and drain it for you.
و يضعها داخل التقرحات الملتهبة و يفرغها
But seriously, seriously, we did get along,
و لكن بكل جدية كنا متفاهمين جدا مع بعض
because we had a common goal of wanting to inspire these young people.
لان همنا المشترك كان الهام هؤلاء الشباب
They were our teammates! They were inspiring us.
لقد كانوا اعضاء في الفريق و كانوا يلهموننا ايضا
The stories we were hearing got us to the South Pole.
لقد اوصلتنا القصص التي سمعناها الى القطب الجنوبي
The website worked brilliantly as a two-way street of communication.
و لقد عمل موقع الانترنت بشكل رائع كطريق للاتصال باتجاهين
Young people in northern Canada, kids in an elementary school,
شباب في شمالي كندا, و صغار في المدارس الابتدائية
dragging sleds across the school-yard,
يجرون الزلاجات عبر ساحات المدارس
pretending they were Richard, Ray and Kevin. Amazing.
يتظاهرون بانهم ريتشارد و راي و كيفن
We arrived at the South Pole. We huddled into that tent,
عندما وصلنا الى القطب الجنوبي, اجتمعنا داخل الخيمة
45 below that day, I'll never forget it.
في درجة حرارة -45 لن انساها ابدا
We looked at each other with these looks
و نظرنا الى بعض بنظرات
of disbelief at what we had just completed.
عدم التصديق لما انجزناه
And I remember looking at the guys thinking,
و اتذكر انني كنت انظر الى زملائي و افكر
"What do I take from this journey?" You know? Seriously.
ماذا تعلمت من هذه الرحلة؟
That I'm this uber-endurance guy?
هل انا رجل تحمل الصعاب
As I stand here today talking to you guys,
كما اقف هنا الان و اتحدث لكم
I've been running for the grand sum of five years.
لقد كنت اركض لمدة 5 سنوات
And a year before that I was a pack-a-day smoker,
و عدة سنوات قبل ذلك كنت ادخن علبة دخان كاملة في اليوم
living a very sedentary lifestyle.
اعيش حياة خاملة
What I take from this journey, from my journeys,
ما الذي استطيع ان اتعلمه من هذه الرحلة و الرحلات الاخرى
is that, in fact,
في الحقيقة هو
within every fiber of my belief standing here,
انني اعلم و بكل ذرة مني و انا اقف امامكم اليوم
I know that we can make the impossible possible.
اننا نستطيع فعل المستحيل
I'm learning this at 40.
اتعلم هذا و انا في عمر الاربعين
Can you imagine? Seriously, can you imagine?
و لكن هل يمكن ان تتخيل ؟ هل يمكن ان تتخيل ؟
Imagine being 13 years old,
تخيل طفل عمره 13 سنة
hearing those words, and believing it.
يسمع هذه الكلمات و يؤمن بها
Thank you very much. Thank you.
شكرا جزيلا لكم , شكرا لكم
(Applause)
تصفيق